בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is דף פ, Daf Pe,
80, and we pick up after the משנה, Mishna, and the משנה
Mishna had a couple of components. Actually, we pick up into the
גמרא, Gemara, we'd gotten a little ahead. We'll do the גמרא Gemara
again just for, just start from the גמרא. Gemara. So the first
part of the משנה Mishna was a recap of an earlier debate
about if one limb of an animal that has a blemish gets
mixed up with unblemished animals. So רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, so there
we're talking about that each one is a distinct act, it's not
like all the blood got mixed together, where you can sort of
say I'm really focusing on the kosher blood, not the non-kosher. Here
each one is a distinct act, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
nevertheless if one limb has already been brought up, you can bring
the rest. You can attribute the בעל מום Baal mum limbs to
the ones that were already brought up. And the חכמים Chachamim disagree.
So here you have the same thing if different bowls of blood
got mixed up. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if one was done,
you can do the rest, and the חכמים Chachamim say no, even
if they were all done except one, you can't do the last
one. You have to be afraid that it's a בעל מום. Baal
mum. So the גמרא Gemara says we'll pick up from the גמרא
Gemara again. אמר רבי אלעזר לא הכשיר רבי אליעזר אלא לשניים שניים.
Amar Rabbi Elazar lo hechshir Rabbi Eliezer ela lishnayim lishnayim. Same thing
we said by the limbs. It's only if you do not only
has one already been brought, but you're doing two at a time.
So because you're doing two at a time, you can say, "A,
I'm going to assume that the one that was already brought was
the bad one. B, is because I'm doing two, and one of
them's got to be good, I'm going to assume the other one
is good as well." אבל אחד אחד לא, Avel echad echad lo,
but each one individually, no, because then that might be the not
good one. מתיב רב דימי, Masiv Rav Dimi, רב דימי Rav Dimi
challenged, חכמים אומרים אפילו קרבו כולן חוץ מאחד מהן ישפך לאמה, Chachamim
omrim afilu karvu kulan chutz me'echad mehen yishapech la'amah, that even if
all the bloods have been thrown except one, spill the last one
out because we have to be concerned it's the bad one. Which
means that for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you can bring the last
one even though it's only one. אמר ליה רבי יעקב לרבי ירמיה
בר תחליפא אסבר לך, Amar leh Rabbi Yaakov l'Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Tachlifa
asber lach, I will explain to you, מאי אחד, Mai echad, what
does it mean if one is left? זוג אחד, Zug echad, one
pair. Okay, which is exactly what we said before by the limbs.
So now the גמרא Gemara says וצריכא, Vetzricha, and you need to
tell me both.
דאיתמר בהא, Di itmar b'ha, had you just told me in the
case, meaning why do you have to have the debate both by
the limbs and the blood? If you had just had a debate
by the limbs, בה קאמר רבי אליעזר משום דעבד בה כפרתו. Ba
ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer mishum de'avad beh kapparato. There רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would say, "All right, I'll let you do the limbs because the
basic קרבן's Korban already been brought and we know like all the
קרבנות Korbanot are כשר, Kosher, and you're not actually doing the act
of actual הקרבת הקרבן Hakravat hakorban with the בעל מום. Baal mum.
It's only the wrapping up of the burning of the limbs. That
I'll allow, and allow you to assume that the בעל מום Baal
mum has already been brought." אבל בהא, Avel be'ha, but here where
it's the basic blood that's being brought, maybe he would say I'm
not going to let you bring the blood of a בעל מום,
Baal mum, I'm not going to use my sort of fiction to
let you do that. So I might say לימא מודו ליה רבנן,
Lima modu leh rabbanan, maybe he'll agree to the rabbis. So you
had to tell me they debated even by the case of blood.
If they had just had debate the case of the blood, בה
קאמרי רבנן, Ba ka'amri rabbanan, that might be why the rabbis oppose
it because we're not going to let you bring a בעל מום,
Baal mum, you know, bring the blood. אבל בהא, Avel be'ha, but
in the other case where you've already brought the blood and the
only question is the limbs,
אימא מודו ליה לרבי אליעזר, Eima modu leh l'Rabbi Eliezer, maybe they'd
agree to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. וצריכא, Vetzricha, so you need to
tell me both. Okay, now we move on. Okay, and then the
continuation of this debate, now of the משנה, Mishna, that was one
thing. Then the משנה Mishna goes on to speak about what happens
if, you know, that if the blood from the קרבנות Korbanot above
got brought below or below got brought above, and so, I'm sorry,
I'm sorry, no, above and below, hold on, I'm sorry,
yes, okay, if the ones above got brought above or or below
got brought above, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer again says, so you
presumably it's all mixed in together. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer just says
you sprinkle above, you sprinkle below, and you say that the stuff
that you're doing that's the wrong, the blood that's mixed in that
doesn't belong in that location should be looked at as water. You're
focusing on the blood that belongs above and then you're doing it
again below and focusing on the blood that belongs below. And the
חכמים Chachamim say no, we don't buy this stuff, "pretend that the
inappropriate blood is water," we're not going to let you do it
even if it's all in a mixture and you have to spill
it all out. Okay, and then we got into a fascinating debate
about בל תוסיף Bal tosef and בל תגרע Bal tigra which we're
not going to focus on right away. Okay, but now we got
this case about it's all mixed together, can you do it all
above and all below or do you have to spill it out?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we
taught over there,
in מסכת פרה, Masechet Parah, צלוחית שנפלו לתוכה מים כל שהוא. Tzluchis
shenaflo l'tocho mayim kol shehu. So you've got a a container, a
bowl that has the water of the, you know, of the ashes
of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, and mixed in, so you have
this perfect, the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah water, the stuff that you're
going to sprinkle on people to purify them from טומאת מת, Tumat
mes, and a little bit of tap water gets mixed in. Okay,
so what do you do? Can you go ahead and still use
it? Because any sprinkling you'll do will not be all the sprinkling
of the water of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it'll have a
little of this tap water mixed in. So רבי אליעזר אומר יזה
שתי הזיות, Rabbi Eliezer omer yaze shtei hazyot, you sprinkle twice on
each person. וחכמים אומרים פסולין, Vachachamim omrim psulin, and the חכמים Chachamim
say you can't use it. בשלמא רבנן, Bishlama rabbanan, we understand the
rabbis, בשלמא רבנן סברי יש בילה. Bishlama rabbanan savri yesh bilah. The
rabbis hold that, now this is an important principle in general on
הלכה. Halacha. Do we assume
that liquid... So we're not dealing with water and oil and we're
also not dealing with a centrifuge. We just want to know if
you drop a drop of tap water into פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
water, are we going to assume completely equal dispersion or not? That's
יש בילה. yesh bilah. Yes, what does the scientist want to tell
us?
Well eventually it will if
you give it
a little while.
It takes time. Okay fine.
Obviously oil and water don't mix.
Right right. But things that are basically the same material. So the
question is do we immediately assume or whatever the גמרא Gemara doesn't
use time as a factor, do we assume that it's basically completely
equal distribution or are we concerned about concentrations? Okay, in equal concentrations.
That's the question of יש בילה yesh bilah means we assume completely
equal distribution and אין בילה ein bilah means that we assume not.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri,
בשלמא רבנן סברי יש בילה. bishlama Rabbanan savri yesh bilah. The Rabbis
hold that it completely equally
distributes. והזאה צריכה שיעור. ve'haza tzricha shiur. And when you sprinkle you
need a minimum amount. Okay now the funny thing about this and
I don't have an answer to this is okay there's a question
when I sprinkle the ashes of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah do I
need a minimum amount? But the assumption also is that if I
need a minimum amount, why don't I just use like a double
amount when I'm sprinkling you? You know what I mean? But the
גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that when you sprinkle you always sprinkle one
unit's worth. Okay. So if you assume that יש—that yesh it's equal
distribution, any sprinkling I do right will not be the full quantity
assuming that I can't do extra. It's not clear why I can't
do extra. Okay so any individual sprinkling I do will be one
unit. But that one unit will only be point nine eight point
nine eight פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it'll be point zero two tap
water. And you need the full amount. And you don't have the
full amount because it's equally distributed. Okay.
So that would imply that there's no there's no ביטול bittul at
all even if you have one drop in a hundred gallons of
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah water?
Right. So that is a good point too that here we're assuming—and
you know that's like an interesting question about ביטול, bittul, can you
say ביטול bittul by something not to remove a problem but to
actually make something valid that wasn't valid? Like let's say for example
like a classic question that I think it was תוספות יום טוב
Tosefot Yom Tov asks. He says let's say you have twenty strings
of ציצית tzitzit that were woven לשמה lishmah and one string that
was woven שלא לשמה shelo lishmah and you mix it all up.
Can you use all of them? You know? Like does ביטול bittul
actually make something give something you know a positive halachic status or
does ביטול bittul just remove as it were like a problematic status?
You know what I mean? So anyway but you're right. We're here
not assuming ביטול bittul and that's an interesting question why not. Okay.
So anyway you don't ביטול bittul with distinct objects?
You can actually can if there are enough. If it's מין במינו
min be'mino and you have—yeah you can. But anyway but whatever the
case might be you know Charlie does ask a good question. We're
not assuming ביטול bittul though here. Okay. So the Rabbis assume you
need a full unit. Presumably you only sprinkle one unit at a
time so it's never going to be good. Any individual sprinkling is
not going to be good. והזאה צריכה שיעור. ve'haza tzricha shiur. ואין
מצטרפין להזאות. ve'ein mitztarfin lehaza'ot. And you can't combine a half of
a unit from one sprinkle to a half of a unit of
another. You need the full unit in each sprinkling. That's why they'll
say it'll never be good. Okay.
So that's their position. אלא רבי אליעזר מאי קסבר? ella Rabbi Eliezer
mai kasavar? Rabbi Eliezer is the more interesting position because Rabbi Eliezer
how is it that you have to use two sprinkles and you
can combine them? Okay so let's figure this out. What does he
hold? אי קסבר אין בילה, ei kasavar ein bilah, you don't you
can't assume equal distribution, כי מזה שתי הזאות מאי הוי? ki maza
shtei haza'ot mai hava? דילמא תרוייהו מיא קמזי. dimma tartaihu mayya kamazi.
So if you so now we're assuming it's not just a little—I
mean I gave you the example a little tap water. But the
case isn't limiting it to it. So let's say you got you
know ten units of tap water mixed in to one hundred units
of you know פרה אדומה Parah Adumah water. For Rabbi Eliezer you
know if you did two sprinkles both of those sprinkles if you
assume unequal distribution might have been one hundred percent tap water. So
how can we assume that they can combine? Okay.
אלא קסבר יש בילה. ella kasavar yesh bilah. So it must be
that he holds right that it's equally distributed because if it's not
equally distributed there's no way you can use two sprinkles. You have
to assume they're all tap water. So it must be he holds
that there is equal distribution. Now אי קסבר אין הזאה צריכה שיעור,
ei kasavar ein hazah tzricha shiur, now if he held that there's
no minimum amount even a tiny amount is good so למה לי
שתי הזאות? lamma li shtei haza'ot? Why would you need two? Right?
Any one sprinkle let it be ninety percent פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
ten percent tap even if it's a tiny bit פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah it should be good. So the fact that you need two
means the fact that two work show it's equal distribution. If it
was unequal all all the two might be completely invalid. The fact
that you need two shows that we don't allow a minimum any
even the tiniest amount. Okay. It's this is very nice how it
deductively figures this out. אלא קסבר הזאה צריכה שיעור, ella kasavar hazah
tzricha shiur, there must be a minimum amount. Fine. But now we
can say so you have a minimum amount, sprinkle number one was
eighty percent. percent פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, sprinkle number two is 80
percent פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, and somehow what obviously now we have
to say is you can combine two separate acts to provide the
minimum amount. Okay, ואי קסבר אין מצטרפין להזאה ve'i kasavar ein mitstarfin
lehazah you can't combine, כי מזה שתי הזאות מאי הוי ki mazah
shtei haza'ot mai havi who cares that you did two? Why are
they combining?
ואינמי מצטרפין להזאה ve'inami mitstarfin lehazah now let's assume he holds fine,
it's equally distributed, you need a minimum amount, you need a full
unit, and you can combine two separate sprinkles. But one minute, מי
יימר דמלי לשיעוריה mi eimar demaleh lishiurei what makes you say that
you've got enough meaning so meaning that meaning because the question here
now is is that like the question is what are the proportions?
The way I give it that it was 20-80, so you know
you've got enough, right? If it's equally distributed then you have two
הזאות haza'ot you have 1.6 units, but the גמרא Gemara wants to
sort of clarify that okay, that you would have to say explicitly
for this to work there needs to be at least 50 percent
פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah water, right? Because any less than 50 percent פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah water, it would be .49 and .49 and you
would not get a full unit. Okay, so that's basically the first
answer. אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish so says ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish oh great timing we have here there's some class going on.
אמר ריש לקיש לעולם יש בילה Amar Reish Lakish le'olam yesh bilah
okay like you said equally distributed, והזאה צריכה שיעור vehazah tserichah shiur
you need a minimum amount, והכא במאי עסקינן כגון שנתערבו אחת באחת
vehacha bemai askinan kegon shenitarvu achat be'achat
it's minimally 50 percent פרה אדומה Parah Adumah water and because it's
minimally oh gosh wonderful because I knew this was a wrong decision
because it is minimally 50 percent פרה אדומה Parah Adumah water therefore
you know that by two sprinklings you're going to get one unit
of... this was
such a big mistake... wrong wrong video... excuse
me
we're trying to have a class...
I'm sorry if you could just like go go where you're going
I'm sorry I don't mean to be rude but we're just trying
to have a class thank you so
black for one second all right yeah all right everyone don't worry
everyone just got here if you want to take pictures of me
and I'll see you all up there I'm sure אלא קסבר הזאה
צריכה שיעור Ella kasavar hazah tserichah shiur
okay
so the גמרא Gemara says like this ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
yeah what a mistake this was all right anyway אמר ריש לקיש
לעולם יש בילה והזאה צריכה שיעור והכא במאי עסקינן כגון שנתערבו אחת
באחת Amar Reish Lakish le'olam yesh bilah vehazah tserichah shiur vehacha bemai
askinan kegon shenitarvu achat be'achat that they're mixed up at least 50
percent of each and if they're at least 50 percent of each
then it's going then it's going to be that what do you
call it then you know you're going to have a full unit.
Fine. רבא אמר לעולם יש בילה Rava amar le'olam yesh bilah
it's mixed up equally okay like we assumed, והזאה אין צריכה שיעור
vehazah ein tserichah shiur
and there is no minimum amount. So if there's no minimum amount,
one really should be good so why do you need two? So
the גמרא Gemara says really one should be enough. וקנסא דקנסו רבנן
כי היכי דלא לשתרשלו uknasa dekenasu rabanan ki heichi d-lo lishtarshelu this
is only rabbinic. The rabbis demanded this in order so that you
should not sort of benefit somehow or should not be sloppy. So
if you're sloppy and you let other water fall in you're going
to have to do a double a double sprinkling. Okay, רב אשי
אמר Rav Ashi amar רב אשי Rav Ashi says אין בילה ein
bilah so that's a second answer, really one is really sufficient. רב
אשי Rav Ashi says אין בילה ein bilah that really it does
not equally distribute. So if it doesn't equally distribute we've got a
question, how could even two be good? Maybe they're all bad, maybe
they're all just tap water. אין בילה יזה שתי הזאות ein bilah
yazah shtei haza'ot
and now what does it so do two? So how does that
help? So רש"י Rashi has a slightly different גרסא girsa by רב
אשי. Rav Ashi. רש"י's Rashi's גרסא girsa by רב אשי Rav Ashi
is that the משנה Mishnah says כל שהוא. kol shehu. Remember when
I started I said it was like .02 tap water. So that's
what רב אשי Rav Ashi says. רב אשי Rav Ashi says there's
a reason it gave the example that a tiny bit of tap
water fell in because because if it's such a tiny bit you
know that after one sprinkling all of even if it's unequally distributed
after one sprinkling it'll all be used up. Okay, meaning the worst
case scenario since basically he's saying that what do you call it
he's basically saying that even a minimum amount is enough
and therefore if a minimum amount is enough the worst case is
that in the in the early sprinklings that you're doing it's all
the tap water. If it's unequally distributed, fine he says, but if
it's only a כל שהוא kol shehu by the time you're done
with the first sprinkling even if that was all the tap water
you've dissolved up and if it's equally distributed then each one it
will at least by the second one you'll have some of the
ashes of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. That's what רב אשי Rav
Ashi says.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this according to רש"י Rashi
yeah so the גמרא Gemara says like this so מתיבי meitivi I'll
ask you on this. רבי אומר Rebbi omer לדברי ר' אלעזר הזאה
כל שהוא מטמא. ledivrei Rabbi Eleazar hazah kol shehu metamei. מטהרת. metaheres.
So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, we say that that even
the that even a tiny bit works. So we said before that
the logic of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was that you needed a
minimum amount, and that at least that was ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish's
approach, and the two minimum amounts, you know, and the two half
ones combined, right? The second two explanations basically said that you needed
even the tiniest bit would be okay, and the only reason to
do it twice is either because it was unequal distribution or just
so you shouldn't be sloppy and you shouldn't benefit. But the first
explanation was you needed a minimum amount and the two halves combined.
Okay, but we've got a ברייתא. braisa. Here's what this ברייתא braisa
teaches: a תוספתא. Tosefta. רבי Rebbi אומר, omer, רבי Rebbi says, לדברי
רבי אליעזר, l'divrei Rabbi Eliezer, הזאה hazah כל שהוא kol shehu מטהרת,
metaheres, that really even the smallest amount works. Okay, הזאה hazah אין
צריכה שיעור, ein tzrichah shiur, and so it's sort of saying the
same point, there's no minimum amount required, and הזאה מחצה כשרה ומחצה
פסולה, hazah mechtza kesherah u'mechtza pesulah, three ways of saying the same
thing. Well actually that last one is a bit is a slightly
different point, that the smallest amount is okay and even if it's
a mixture, some of כשר kosher פרה אדומה parah adumah water and
some of tap water, right, even if it's a mixture, then it's
going to be, what do you call it, then that's okay as
long as there's some small amount.
Right, exactly. So רבי Rebbi basically says an answer that would work
for answer number two or answer number three. He basically says that
the smallest amount works. So why do you need to do it
twice? Either it's some type of a fine so you shouldn't benefit
or because it's what do you call
it or because the other explanation given was that it was unequal
distribution. Okay, and therefore but it certainly rejects ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish's
position because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said that there is a minimum
amount and you need to combine the two halves. Okay, so that
rejects ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. ועוד תניא, v'od tanya, we taught it
in another ברייתא, braisa, top of עמוד ב', amud beis, ועוד תניא,
v'od tanya, בהדיא, behedya, הניתנין למעלה שנתערבו בניתנין למטה. hanitnin l'ma'ala shenisavu
banitnin l'mata.
So if those were things that were put above that were mixed
up with things that were put below, now we're tying this into
our משנה, Mishnah, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר, omer, יתן למעלה והתחתונים
עלו לו. yiten l'ma'ala v'hatachtonim alu lo.
So you go ahead and you put the stuff above, okay, and
that counts for the part of the mixture that belongs above. And
then so now what we're going to try to prove is the
way רש"י Rashi explains what we're doing here, but pretty soon we
forget this whole discussion of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Okay, but
what we're trying to do is decide between position number two and
position number three by the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Remember position number
two and position number three both agree that a tiny amount was
okay, but position number two said the reason you do it twice
is just so you shouldn't be sloppy. Position number three said the
reason you do it twice is because of a possible unequal distribution,
and the first one might have all been the tap water. Okay,
remember that? So the basic thing we're going to focus on now,
so bracket the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, we've rejected ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish at least for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's based on the
fact that a כל שהוא kol shehu works. Okay, and the basic
issue at this stage was, was whether what do you call
it, was whether for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you assume יש בילה
yeish bila or אין בילה, ein bila, between position two and three.
So let's just ask that question and now we're just going to
go with that question and ask on the משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה
Mishnah has the different bloods getting mixed up and you put some
above and some below. So the position רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer basically
says it all works. The one when you put it above you've
got some of the above blood there, we ignore the non- the
blood below, when you put it below you've got the below blood
and it all works. So the point is all of that work
would only make sense if we assume יש בילה, yeish bila, if
we assume there's an equal distribution. If we don't assume that there's
an equal distribution, maybe when you're doing the stuff above it's all
the below blood, when you're doing the stuff below it's all the
above blood. So forget now the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, we're done
with the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Now the point is let's look
at the משנה Mishnah and determine whether according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, cause that was the debate by the question of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer by פרה אדומה, parah adumah, let's determine whether יש בילה
yeish bila and אין בילה. ein bila. And the simple sense of
all the sources is of course יש בילה yeish bila and we'll
see if the גמרא Gemara has a way of getting out of
it. Yes.
So you can question whether there's יש בילה yeish bila if you
just let it sit there, because you could certainly stir it.
Yeah, I think that's a good point. That's what I said before
about the sink fish thing. Like I think the גמרא Gemara with
the יש בילה yeish bila doesn't feel like it's either like yes
or no, it's funny. Like it goes to one extreme or the
other, it doesn't consider questions about passage of time or stirring or
anything like that. I don't know how to explain that. Okay, so
let's take a look. ותניא בהדיא, v'sanya behedya, and this is going
to try to prove the idea of יש בילה. yeish bila. הניתנין
למעלה שנתערבו בניתנין למטה, hanitnin l'ma'ala shenisavu banitnin l'mata,
things that belong above were mixed with things that go below. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר omer יתן למעלה yiten l'ma'ala the first, והתחתונים
עלו לו, v'hatachtonim alu lo, and then when you get to the
stuff below that also counts. Okay, now presumably it counts for the
for the for the sacrifices that belong below. ואי אמרת אין בילה,
v'i amart ein bila, if you think that according to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer there's no בילה, bila, אמאי עלו לו, amai alu lo,
why does the stuff below work? דילמא כי יהיב
עליונים למטה ותחתונים למעלה, dilma ki yaiv elyonim l'mata v'tachtonim l'ma'ala,
maybe you got it all reversed. Okay. הגמרא Gemara says הכא במאי
עסקינן כגון דאיכא רובי עליונים hacha bemai askinan kegon d'ika rubi elyonim
וכי יהיב. למעלה שיעור תחתונים ועוד. vechi yaheiv lemala shiur tachtonim ve'od,
Ah, so the case here is that you have the following, you've
got the majority belongs above, so you've got of the of the
above sacrifices, the חטאות, chata'ot, you have 60% of the blood of
חטאות chata'ot and 40% of the עולה. olah. Let's talk about it
as units. You've got six units of חטאות chata'ot and four units
of עולה. olah. So when you put the above blood above, you
put four and a half units. So if you put four and
a half units above, you know that you have some חטאות chata'ot
blood that you've put above. Got it? Because you have most here
have four units of עולה olah blood. So you're going to put
four and a half units above. Now when you go below, okay,
you're going to be spilling the blood of the remaining blood of
the חטאות chata'ot below. Even if what you did above was all
חטאות chata'ot blood, you have a unit and a half left of
חטאות chata'ot blood. So you have anywhere between five and a half
to a unit and a half of units left of חטאות chata'ot
blood, right? Because there were six of חטאת chatat and it was
four of עולה olah and you put four and a half above.
So you spill the rest below, so you now know at least
for the חטאות, chata'ot, you put some חטאות chata'ot blood above and
you've definitely spilled חטאות chata'ot blood below. You know you've done the
חטאות chata'ot correctly. What you have not necessarily know you've done correctly
is the עולה, olah, because it could be you did all of
the עולה olah blood above. You did four and a half units,
it could be four of those units was עולה olah blood. So
now, if we're working with the possibility of אין בילה, ein bilah,
what we're going to say is is that what do you call
it, is that if we're working with the possibility of אין בילה,
ein bilah, we're going to say that the only thing that's good
in this scenario is the חטאות. chata'ot. So although the משנה Mishnah
sounds, the sense you get from the משנה Mishnah is that it's
all good, we're going to explain it actually that only the חטאות
chata'ot is good. Okay, so let's take a look. ואי אמרת אין
בילה, ve'i amrat ein bilah, if you say that there's not an
equal mix, אמאי עלו לו, amai alu lo, why did it count?
דילמא כי יהיב עליונים למטה ותחתונים למעלה, dilma ki yaheiv elyonim lemata
vetachtonim lemala, maybe you're putting the above blood below and the below
blood above. So הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאיכא רובי עליונים, hacha bemai
askinan kegon de'ika rubei elyonim, the majority is the top blood, so
six units of חטאות chata'ot blood. וכי יהיב v'ki yaiv. למעלה שיעור
תחתונים ועוד, lemala shiur tachtonim ve'od. and above you put four and
four units of עולה olah and above you do four four units
and a little bit. So the גמרא Gemara says והתחתונים עלו לו
קתני, vehatachtonim alu lo katani, but it says when you go below
it works. So the גמרא Gemara says לשם שיריים, leshem shirayim, no
it doesn't mean that it works for the bottom sacrifices, the עולות
olot don't work, it means when you spill the remainder below it
works as a spilling of the שיריים shirayim for the עולה olah
blood. Okay, so if you're going to say that you have to
assume unequal distribution, you're never going to make everything okay. Okay, and
the only so so that's the that's answer number one, it's obviously
not פשט. pshat. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear.
נתן למטה ולא נמלך. natan lemata velo nimlach. רבי אליעזר אומר יחזור
ויתן למעלה והתחתונים עלו לו. Rabbi Eliezer omer yachzor veyiten lemala vehatachtonim
alu lo. So let's say you put it below and you didn't
ask permission. Okay, you went ahead and you did it. Okay, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says go ahead and put above and the stuff
at the bottom worked. So again, the simple sense is it all
got mixed together and and everything worked. You did it initially at
the bottom, now you're doing it at the top and presumably it
works for both sacrifices. So the גמרא Gemara is going to give
the same answer. הכא נמי ברובי עליונים וכי יהיב למעלה שיעור תחתונים
ועוד. hacha nami berubei elyonim vechi yaheiv lemala shiur tachtonim ve'od. No,
same case. The case is is that it's six units of חטאות,
chata'ot, four units of עולה, olah, and when he says go put
it above, you started below, now he says put it above, he
means put four units and a little bit above. So the גמרא
Gemara says והתחתונים עלו לו קתני, vehatachtonim alu lo katani, but doesn't
it say that the but doesn't it say that the that the
bottom stuff works? So the גמרא Gemara and again it assumes that
means it works for the bottom sacrifices. So the גמרא Gemara says
לשם שיריים. leshem shirayim. No, for the spilling of the remainder. Now
here you have a fascinating thing though, because right now it seems
boring, it seems like we just repeated what we said before, right?
And that we made it that it only worked for the stuff
above. But here's the problem or the issue. Here the order was,
first you did below and then you did above. So if it
says that the bottom worked for שיריים, shirayim, can you have the
spilling of שיריים shirayim before you have the actual placing of the
blood itself? שיריים shirayim normally means the remainder. So let's go say,
I take some חטאות chata'ot blood, I'm I'm going to spill a
little bit at the base and now I'm going to do the
the rest of it at the top, was I יוצא yotzei my
obligation of שיריים? shirayim? You would assume not. רש"י Rashi seems to
read this גמרא Gemara that that's what the גמרא Gemara is actually
arguing, that now that you did the stuff above, you were retroactively
יוצא yotzei שיריים shirayim even though you spilled the שיריים shirayim first
below. תוספות Tosafot says no, we would have to read what this
means is after you do the above, you go back and you
do it below again. Okay, so to one hand this sounds like
it's just a repeat of what we said before, but you read
the גמרא Gemara in the simple sense, it seems to be saying
that actually what you if you first did it below that can
count as שיריים shirayim even before you've done the stuff at the
top. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear. נתן למעלה ולא נמלך. natan lemala
velo nimlach. You did it above and you and you didn't ask
permission. אלו ואלו מודים שיחזור ויתן למטה. elu ve'elu modim sheyachzor veyiten
lemata.
Everybody agrees in this case, even the Rabbis that disagree with רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and say we don't let you do stuff where
it doesn't belong and pretend that it's just water, here they would
agree because if you started above, so now you can do everything
else below, you can take all the remainder below. Because it's a
mixture of חטאת Chatas and עולה Olah blood, you spill it below,
you throw it below, the עולה Olah blood counts as עולה Olah
blood, and the חטאת Chatas blood, why can you do that לכתחילה
lechatchila below? Because what are you supposed to do now with the
remainder of the חטאת Chatas blood? Pour it out below. So here
the חכמים Chachamim actually agree to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer if you
didn't ask and you started above, then the חכמים Chachamim are going
to let you finish below. Okay, got it? Because then either way
it works. אלו ואלו Eilu ve'eilu so it says והא אלו ואלו
עלו לו קתני. Veha eilu ve'eilu alu lo katani. I'm sorry I
skipped a line. אלו ואלו Eilu ve'eilu ויתן למטה veyiten lemata and
so they all agree that you can go ahead and do it
below because now you've got both.
It works just for the חטאת, Chatas, it doesn't work to...
well, based on what we've been saying about בילה, bila, right, meaning
best case scenario, it's equally distributed and it worked for both, and
worst case scenario, it's going to work for the חטאת. Chatas. Okay?
But the חכמים Chachamim wouldn't have a problem with you putting it
below, because either blood that you've got left here will work for
the חטאת. Chatas. But we haven't said that yet. The simple sense
is of course that it works for both. Okay? והא
אלו ואלו עלו לו, Veha eilu ve'eilu alu lo, and that's the
next line. They both counted. So that last line actually makes it
clear that both of them did work. So that's a pretty darn
good proof that for... that יש בילה. yeish bila. So the גמרא
Gemara says הכי נמי ברובו יין וכיוצא למעלה שיר תחתונים
ועוד. hachi nami beruvo yayin vechayotze lemala shir tachtonim ve'od. Says no,
no, no, it's one of these scenarios again that you did six
units and four units and four and a bit etc. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, the ברייתא braisa is explicit. והא אלו ואלו
עלו לו קתני. Veha eilu ve'eilu alu lo katani. The ברייתא braisa
explicitly says both count. And the only way both are going to
count is if we assume equal distribution. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says no קתני. katani. So the גמרא Gemara says סיפא אתאן לרבנן
דאמרי... seifa atan lerabbanan de'amri...
I'm sorry, מי קתני אלו ואלו מודים אלו ואלו עלו לו? Mi
katani eilu ve'eilu modim eilu ve'eilu alu lo? Ha! It doesn't say
both combined. It doesn't say the rabbis agree to רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that both count. It says the rabbis agree to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that you could do it at the bottom, period. And
they both count. So the last line where it says and they
both count, so קתני סיפא אתאן לרבנן דאמרי יש בילה. katani seifa
atan lerabbanan de'amri yeish bila.
The last line where it says they both count is for the
rabbis. We're not going to debate that the rabbis say it does
equally distribute. Our question was רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's position, because remember
it's all going back to that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by the
חטאת Chatas water. So for the rabbis we're willing to concede יש
בילה. yeish bila. So in this case you didn't ask, it got
mixed together, and you did it above without asking, go do it
below. Because you know why you can do it below? Because it
works for the חטאת Chatas and it works for the עולה. Olah.
And for the רבנן Rabbanan that יש בילה, yeish bila, they both
work... you... both sacrifices were good. Okay?
So... so...
so both sacrifices were good. So... but for what do you call
it, but for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, maybe not. For רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer you do it below, it counted for the חטאת Chatas
because it was a majority חטאת, Chatas, but maybe it didn't count
for the עולה. Olah. Okay? So again the simple sense of everything
of course is יש בילה yeish bila and you can always assume
you have both of them mixed together, etc., etc. For the rabbis
clearly it says אלו ואלו עלו לו, eilu ve'eilu alu lo, both
work, that means יש בילה. yeish bila. We're just continuing to argue
that it's possible for רבי אליעזר אין בילה, Rabbi Eliezer ein bila,
and that the scenarios where they work is that there was a
majority of חטאת, Chatas, and it works for the חטאת Chatas and
it doesn't work for the עולה. Olah. Okay yes.
So you're... you throw some...
you throw blood on the top and there's the possibility that there's
no עולה Olah blood left because we don't hold... we hold אין...
ein... or at least רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer may hold אין בילה.
ein bila. But the blood that's on the top is eventually going
to fall... go to fall down to the bottom. Right? So would
that...
no, the חטאת Chatas blood doesn't eventually... well what do you mean?
I don't... one more time, what's your question?
So you're throwing the חטאת Chatas blood above... right... it's got to
go somewhere and eventually it's going to trickle down.
No, it trickles down to the סובב. sovev. To the סובב sovev
it stops there. But... but what's your point anyway? No, that would
not count for זריקת עולה zrikat olah blood. No. Yeah that's my...
that was my question. No, you have to... no that trickle down
at most could count for שפיכת שיריים. shfichat shirayim. But anyway it's
going to hit the סובב. sovev. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: okay תא
שמע. ta shema. So we're still trying to prove whether רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer holds יש בילה. yeish bila. הניתנים במתנה אחת שנתערבו בניתנים
במתנה אחת
ינתנו במתנה אחת. Hanitannim bematana achat shenitarvu benitannim bematana achat yinantnu bematana
achat.
So blood of for for like a בכור bechor gets mixed up
with a מעשר. ma'aser. They both require one application. So you do
one application. So the question is why can you do one application?
That works if יש בילה. yeish bila. But if it's אין בילה
ein bila maybe you're doing all of one קרבן korban and not
the other, right? So again simple sense is יש בילה yeish bila
and this is again רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because it's clear from
the end of the משנה Mishnah that this is רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer holds of this position. So the גמרא Gemara says ואי אמרת
אין בילה... ve'ei amrat ein bila... if you say there's no בילה,
bila, אמאי ינתנו במתנה אחת? amai yinantnu bematana achat? Why is one
enough? דילמא מהאי קיהיב ומהאי לא קיהיב. dilma mehai kahiv umehai lo
kahiv. Maybe you're giving... maybe it's only of the בכור, bechor, not
of the מעשר. ma'aser.
So גמרא Gemara says כגון שנתערבו אחת באחת. kegon shenitarvu achat be'achat.
So they're equal, one unit of each. But the point is so
what if it's one unit of each? So what? Maybe you're doing
one and not the other. So what רש"י Rashi says and then
this is a very strange read of the משנה Mishnah is that...
It's one unit of each, and when it says you give one
מתנה, matanah, it means you give one מתנה matanah for each קרבן.
korban. So you have a unit of מעשר maaser blood gets mixed
up with a unit of בכור bechor blood, so do one מתנה
matanah for מעשר maaser and one מתנה matanah for בכור bechor and,
you
know, meaning so it's basically, basically what it's saying is use all
of the blood, you know, do it, you know, you have two
units and put both units on the מזבח mizbeach and therefore whatever
the distribution is, some of the blood of the חטאת chatat is
going to get there and some of the blood of the—I mean
some of the blood of the בכור bechor and some of the
blood of the מעשר. maaser. Not a very good read of the
משנה. mishnah. מתן ארבע במתן ארבע, matan arba b'matan arba, four and
four gets mixed up. So it says you do a placing of
four. So the גמרא Gemara says how can that be? Maybe it's
all unequally distributed. הכא נמי שנתערבו ארבע בארבע. hacha nami she'nitarvu arba
b'arba.
So it's equal amounts, four and four. So what if it's equal
amounts? But still, it's maybe, maybe you didn't do it. So again
רש״י Rashi says when the משנה mishnah says if four and four
gets mixed up, do four, it means do four twice. So basically
what the משנה mishnah is just saying is it all got mixed
up, go do what you would normally do. You would normally have
done four for one and four for the other. It's all mixed
up, do four for one and four for the other. Okay, and
you don't know how the distribution works out but at the end
of the day you're going to get it all on the altar.
Okay.
Okay,
next. מתן ארבע במתנה אחת, matan arba b'matanah achat, four gets mixed
up with one. And here's where we get the debate about בל
תוסיף bal tosif and בל תגרע. bal tigra. Do you do four,
do you do one? Right. Now here by the way and here
the problem is is that here it's going to be a challenge
because here it's clear that you don't do four and one because
the whole debate of בל תוסיף bal tosif and בל תגרע bal
tigra makes it clear that you're either according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer you're doing four applications or two that are four. According to
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua you're doing one. You're not doing all the
applications, right? So if you have to be concerned about unequal distribution,
right, how does doing four work? Let's say the stuff that required
the one was all left over behind or something, okay, how's it
all going to work? So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא הכא
נמי בנתערבו באחת, v'chi teima hacha nami b'nitarvu b'achat, it's exactly four
getting mixed up with exactly one unit. אי הכי אמר לו רבי
יהושע הרי הוא עובר
על בל תוסיף הכא בל תוסיף מהיכא. ei hachi amar lo Rabbi
Yehoshua harei hu over al bal tosif hacha bal tosif meihacha. Now
what does that mean?
So this is again very hard for רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
to exactly figure out.
But רש״י Rashi says like this, if four got mixed up with
one,
so you've got five units here, you're going to do four applications
of blood. Each application is going to be one and a quarter
units, okay, because it's clear that we're not doing four plus one.
That would then get us into the בל תוסיף bal tosif בל
תגרע bal tigra possible issue or whatever. Anyway, so here you're doing
four and a quarter—each—four applications each one with one and a quarter.
So the assumption is is that's good because that accounts for the
one because eventually that whole unit got on the מזבח, mizbeach, okay,
and that's why it should count for the one.
But then the question is, why is there בל תוסיף? bal tosif?
Now why shouldn't there be בל תוסיף? bal tosif? So רש״י Rashi
says well because if there's only exactly one unit there's not בל
תוסיף bal tosif because you just put the one unit on the
מזבח. mizbeach. Who cares that maybe you put it, you know, in
multiple places? You know, meaning the רש״י's Rashi understanding that the גמרא's
Gemara question is that the problem with בל תוסיף bal tosif is
that you're doing more than one unit on the altar which is
strange because the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara is that the
problem of בל תוסיף bal tosif is something that only should have
been on one corner you're putting it on four corners. So that
could be exactly the same issue here. There's five units, you're distributing
it on four corners, the stuff got spread out on multiple corners,
why shouldn't there be בל תוסיף? bal tosif? It's not clear why
the גמרא Gemara feels that by reading it this way somehow there's
no בל תוסיף. bal tosif. The way תוספות Tosafot explains it is
the following,
okay. תוספות Tosafot says that—let me see if I can get this
right—תוספות Tosafot says that we're going to assume that there
needs to be a minimum amount of blood on the altar, enough
blood that it would be visible, like, you know, that you should
could see the mark that it left or something of that nature,
so there's a minimum amount. Now the case here, let me see
if I can get this right, the case here is like this.
If we assume, so if we assume unequal distribution, okay, and if
we assume that there are two units that got mixed up, wait,
I gotta think how I get this straight. If we assume that
there are two units that get mixed up... okay hold on
let me see if I can get this straight.
Okay, here's how it works, okay. So remember, you're doing two that
are four, right? The four is really two, okay. So we—תוספות Tosafot
says we were assuming like this, when we weren't saying that exactly
one and one got mixed up or four and four got mixed
up, because remember we tried to limit the amount of the mixture
in order to make it work of אין בילה, ein bilah, right?
It wasn't just a lot got mixed up, it was a precise
amount and you got it all on the altar. So before we
were assuming that it made sense. You got a lot of the
one unit, a lot of the—the—the one
getting... that there's a minimum amount here and a minimum amount here
and you were בל תוסיף, bal tosif, you basically did the one,
the thing that should have been one, you did it on two
corners, okay. That would have made sense. But if you basically have
just one unit getting mixed up in four, alright, so, or then
תוספות Tosafot says or maybe actually תוספות Tosafot says maybe it's two
units getting mixed up in four, whatever, he then it says we
can understand why basically then he says I don't understand why why
this is a problem of בל תוסיף bal tosif because it's because
it's unlikely, if you say that stuff is unequally distributed, right, then
the possibility that it's exactly equally distributed is minuscule, right? So if
it's exactly equally distributed and you got two units mixed up, it'll
be בל תוסיף, bal tosif, right? because one unit in each application,
you know there'll be one unit of the one blood in each
one. But any other scenario there's going to be not enough of
the other of the one blood in the other application, so it
won't be two applications. Am I being clear? Like you understand? So
basically what תוספות Tosafot says is if you assumed יש בילה, yesh
bilah, I get why there's a בל תוסיף bal tosif concern, because
there's a lot of blood of both types mixed up, you did
the two applications, and the blood that was should only have been
one corner had a minimum amount here and a minimum amount here
and it was בל תוסיף bal tosif on two corners. But in
the way you've been trying to be very precise, that it's only
a certain amount that are getting mixed up, it's not a lot
getting mixed up.
So even if we assume basically that two units got mixed up,
if two units get mixed up of the one application blood, you
know the קרבן korban is כשר kasher because you throw on two
corners and whatever the distribution is, right, even if it's all here,
all there, equally distributed, no matter what the distribution is, you got
the blood on a corner and the קרבן korban is כשר. kasher.
But the only scenario of בל תוסיף bal tosif is the minuscule
possibility that it was exactly equally divided. Any other scenario you'll have
you won't have enough on the other corner to be a problem.
So why therefore says תוספות Tosafot given the way you're reading it
should we be concerned about בל תוסיף? bal tosif? All right, anyway,
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. All right, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says.
So אלא, ella, so anyway, based on all these reads, it's very
hard to read that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't hold like בילה.
bilah. It really sounds that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds like בילה.
bilah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא, ella amar
Rava, so rather רבא Rava says בבלולים לא פליגי. be-belulim lo peligi.
If it actually... you know what, you're right. If it... well not
you're right. If it was mixed up, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't
hold of בילה bilah and we'd have to give some of those
answers we gave before. But I'm going to give you better answers
to all the questions you just asked rather than oh it only
works for the חטאת, chatat, it only works for this. I'm going
to give you a better answer to all those scenarios. If it
were mixed up, you're right, the story would be a different story.
כי פליגי בכוסות. ki peligi be-khosot. The discussions here about this stuff
and put it above and put it below and it counts or
whatever is not that it mixed up, all the liquid is mixed
together. In that case we'd have to be afraid of unequal distribution.
So what are we talking about? That it's various bowls got mixed
up, okay? So and when we say put the stuff above, what
we mean here is I've got two bowls. One is חטאת chatat
blood, one is עולה olah blood. When we say put it above,
we mean put from both bowls above. And when we say put
it below, we mean put from both bowls below. So in that
scenario, if it were all mixed up, we'd have to be afraid
unequal distribution and you don't know you got from each one in
each place. But because it's separate bowls, then you know you're going
to tell you put from both bowls in both places, right, and
the same with the four and the one. The bowls got mixed
up, it's not the liquid got mixed up. And that's why we
have to be concerned about בל תוסיף bal tosif and all these
types of things because you are knowing that you are putting from
each blood in each place. Okay, and that's how come you don't
have to you can't prove from here בילה bilah because because maybe
it is unequal distribution but we're knowing but we're dealing with separate
bowls so of course it's going to be equal you're going to
be putting from both of them in both places.
רבי אליעזר אית ליה רואין Rabbi Eliezer it lei ro'in לרבנן לית
להו רואין. la-Rabbanan leit lehu ro'in. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds of
רואין ro'in and the רבנן Rabbanim don't hold of רואין, ro'in, meaning
about whether you can view the inappropriate blood as water. Okay,
and therefore basically that's the point. Meaning that the debate is not
about a בילה bilah debate, the debate everybody you're giving from both
כוסות, kosot, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is okay to give from the
כוס kos that doesn't belong because we'll look at it like water
and the רבנן Rabbanim are not. But בבלולים לא פליגי. be-belulim lo
peligi. You can't prove maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't hold of
בילה bilah but all your questions go off because the case there
were separate vessels, not mixed up water. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says והתניא ve-ha-tanya בבלולים לא פליגי, be-belulim lo peligi, do they really
not debate
בילה? bilah? והתניא אמר רבי יהודה לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר וחכמים על
דם חטאת שנתערב בדם עולה שיקרב. ve-ha-tanya amar Rabbi Yehuda lo necheleku
Rabbi Eliezer ve-Chakhamim al dam chatat she-nitarev be-dam olah she-yikarev. Okay, so
remember before we had the same issue by the limbs of the
sacrifice that got mixed up where the משנה Mishnah sort of, you
know, said like oh if it's a בעל מום... ba'al mum... where
the משנה Mishnah sort of said like, oh, if it's a בעל
מום, baal mum, there רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if one did
it you could do the rest. And then we had another ברייתא
brayta says no, no, no, by a בעל מום baal mum actually
everybody's okay, the debate is by a, you know, is about when
it's worse of a פסול, psul, רובע ונרבע. rova ve-nirva. You might
remember we had the same issue by the cases of the limbs,
right, where exactly was the locus of their debate. So we're going
to say the same here by the blood.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara says like this. והתניא, Ve-hatanya, אמר רבי יהודה:
Amar Rabbi Yehuda: לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר וחכמים על דם חטאת שנתערב
בדם עולה שיקרב. Lo nechelku Rabbi Eliezer va-chachamim al dam chatat she-nisarev
be-dam olah she-yikarev. Nobody disagrees by if the blood of a חטאת
chatat and עולה olah got mixed up, that there you do it
above, you do it below, it's not a bad thing, it's not
a בעל מום. baal mum. So you can go ahead and do
it, no problem. ברובע ונרבע שלא יקרב, Be-rova ve-nirva she-lo yikarev, and
everybody agrees that if it's something that like was in an act
of bestiality, you can't use it. על מה נחלקו? Al mah nechelku?
על דם תמימים שנתערב בדם בעל מום. Al dam tmimim she-nisarev be-dam
baal mum.
The debate is by a case of blood of an unblemished with
blood of a blemished. שרבי אליעזר אומר יקרב בין בבלה be-valla בין
בכוסות. She-Rabbi Eliezer omer yikarev bein be-valla bein be-khosot. Rabbi Eliezer says
go ahead and do that, whether it's separate vessels that got mixed
up or whether it's the bloods that got mixed up. וחכמים אומרים
לא יקרב. Ve-chachamim omrim lo yikarev. No, you can't do it. Okay,
so anyway, but what interests us right now is that it's clear
for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, even though he shifts the debate, that
they're not just acting by חטאת chatat and עולה olah they're not
debating, they're only debating by בעל מום. baal mum. And he says
no, no, no, חטאת chatat and עולה, olah, we've been saying חטאת
chatat and עולה olah they debate. He says חטאת chatat and עולה
olah they don't debate, they only debate by בעל מום. baal mum.
But what's more, but what's interesting for us is that he's saying
that the debate is whether it's the liquids got mixed up or
the vessels got mixed up. So you see that they're debating even
the case where the liquids got mixed up, and that makes all
these problems because it sounds like from there we should be able
to infer that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds יש בילה yesh bilah
because the simple reading of all those cases is יש בילה. yesh
bilah. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, that's רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda's position. רבי יהודה אליבא דרבי אליעזר מסיק בין בבלה בין
בכוסות. Rabbi Yehuda aliba de-Rabbi Eliezer masik bein be-valla bein be-khosot. Fine,
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it's true, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds
his position even by mixed up. Okay, and for רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda you have to give all those bad answers that we gave
before. ורבנן בכוסות פליגי. Ve-rabbanan be-khosot pligi. Okay, but the Rabbis would
say they only argue when the vessels got mixed up. So again,
when the vessels got mixed up and you're giving from each vessel,
you know all the blood's got in each places. Okay, and therefore
that might be all the scenarios, that the vessels got mixed up.
And maybe if the bloods got mixed up, maybe it won't work
because we have to assume אין בילה ein bilah and it's unequal
distribution. And if you want to assume that there are cases where
it can work by the bloods get mixed up, you have to
give the more forced answers that we gave before, you know, that
there were six units and four units and you did four and
a little bit, etc., etc. Okay, so all of this was a
long discussion
which somehow we got onto it from the חטאת chatat case. But
the basic point of this whole discussion was that the simple sense
of course of the משנה Mishnah is that the bloods get distributed
equally, okay, that's the simple sense, but the what do you call
it, but the גמרא Gemara says and that's יש בילה, yesh bilah,
but the גמרא Gemara says it's possible אין בילה. ein bilah. So
how does it work in the משנה? Mishnah? So it had a
couple of possibilities, right? One possibility was it works because basically it's
four units and six units and you do four and a little
bit and it only works for the חטאת chatat and it doesn't
work for the עולה. olah. And assuming it works for both, which
is the simple sense, then the case is that the vessels got
mixed up and you put from both vessels. Okay, but again, the
simple sense is that יש בילה. yesh bilah. And the other thing
which we're going to pick up tomorrow is that once you did
it above, everybody agrees you could do it below because then you're
doing both the עולה olah properly and the remainder of the חטאת
chatat properly. Okay, and that will sort of pick up tomorrow.